Much is said of Sao Paulo's multiculturalism
Muito se fala de São Paulo, de sua multiculturalidade,
and of its diverse population,
das diversas populações que aqui habitam,
but very little is spoken of the black population.
mas pouco se fala da população preta.
Why? The historical process in in Sao Paulo has been different
Por que?
from Rio de Janeiro's and Salvador's, that were capital cities.
Em São Paulo o processo foi diferente do Rio de Janeiro e de Salvador, que eram capitais.
In Sao Paulo, the black population still arrived in great numbers
Em São Paulo a população preta entra em massa
when slavery had already started to be called into question. With the
num momento em que a escravidão já está sendo contestada
beginning of the coffee surge and the ending of the international slave trade,
ou seja, com o ciclo do café e o final do tráfico internacional,
from where did the biggest share of the black population come from?
de onde que vem a maios parte da população preta de São Paulo?
It came from the so called interprovincial slave trade,
Veio do chamado tráfico interprovincial.
by which black people who were dismissed from Rio's and northeast plantations
Ou seja, eram os pretos que eram dispensados das lavouras do rio e do nordeste em crise
and sent here to Sao Paulo.
e pra cá habitaram.
Every city with a big share of black population
Todas as cidades que tinham um contingente grande da população preta
has gone through massive processes of gentrification,
passaram por um amplo processo de gentrificação,
racial and social segregation.
segregação racial, segregação social.
It couldn't have been different with Sao Paulo.
São Paulo não poderia ser diferente.
However, we also know
Mas, como a gente sabe também
that capitalism has developed in the most literal meaning of the word
é aqui em São Paulo que o capitalismo vai se desenvolver
here in Sao Paulo.
nas chamas formas mais plenas de capitalismo.
Capitalism established new social relations of production.
Bom, o capitalismo chega com novas relações sociais de produção.
A new workforce is necessary to comply with that. That's the reason of
. É necessário uma nova força de trabalho. Daí o projeto de imigração
the immigration project, which is meant to whiten the population.
pra branquear a população.
The impact of the gentrification process on the indigenous and black populations
O processo de gentrificação da população preta e da população indígena
is historical and it's still ongoing.
é contínuo e histórico.
The very same process, for over 500 years.
Há mais de 500 anos, o mesmo processo.